# Giuseppe **Attanasio**

#### POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · INSTITUTO DE TELECOMUNICAÇÕES

Universidade de Aveiro Campus Universitário de, R. Santiago, 3810-193 Aveiro

② g8a9 | ☐ giuseppe-attanasio | У @peppeatta | ► Scholar

"Computers aren't the thing. They are the thing that gets us to the thing." - Halt And Catch Fire

### Bio

I am a Postdoctoral Researcher in the SARDINE at the Instituto de Telecomunicações, University of Lisbon. My research interests lay at the intersection of interpretability, fairness, and safety.

In my spare time, I like reading and watching Sci-Fi, playing basketball. I am also into DIY and 3D printing. I am a failed guitarist and pizzaiolo.

I update my website more frequently than this document, with recent professional news, projects, and publications

## Education \_

**University of Lisbon** 

POSTDOC AT INSTITUTO DE TELECOMUNICAÇÕES

• PI: André Martins

**Bocconi University** 

POSTDOC AT DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTING SCIENCES

• Pl: Debora Nozza Advisor: Dirk Hovy

Politecnico di Torino

Ph.D. AT DEPARTMENT OF CONTROL AND COMPUTER ENGINEERING

• Advisor: Elena Baralis Politecnico di Torino

MD IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING, DATA SCIENCE TRACK

• Grade: 110/110 cum Laude

Politecnico di Torino

**BD IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING** 

• Grade: 110/110

Lisbon, Portugal

Feb. 2024 - ongoing

Milan, Italy Oct. 2022 - Feb. 2024

Torino, Italy

Nov. 2018 - Oct. 2022

Torino, Italy Oct. 2016 - Oct. 2018

Torino, Italy

Oct. 2013 - Oct. 2016

## **Publications**

I firmly believe in open-access research. Most of my papers are free to read, and code and data are opensource under permissive license, whenever possible. All the pointers are collected on my website.

## Selected

Giuseppe Attanasio et al. "A Tale of Pronouns: Interpretability Informs Gender Bias Mitigation for Fairer Instruction-Tuned Machine Translation". In: Proceedings of the 2023 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing. Ed. by Houda Bouamor, Juan Pino, and Kalika Bali. Singapore: Association for Computational Linguistics, Dec. 2023, pp. 3996-4014. DOI: 10.18653/v1/2023.emnlp-main.243. URL: https://aclanthology.org/2023.emnlp-main.243

Giuseppe Attanasio et al. "Entropy-based Attention Regularization Frees Unintended Bias Mitigation from Lists". İn: Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics: ACL 2022. Dublin, Ireland: Association for Computational Linguistics, May 2022, pp. 1105–1119. DOI: 10.18653/v1/2022.findings-acl.88. URL: https://aclanthology.org/2022.findings-acl.88

Giuseppe Attanasio et al. "ferret: a Framework for Benchmarking Explainers on Transformers". In: *Proceedings of the 17th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: System Demonstrations*. Dubrovnik, Croatia: Association for Computational Linguistics, May 2023, pp. 256–266. URL: https://aclanthology.org/2023.eacl-demo.29

Federico Bianchi et al. Safety-Tuned LLaMAs: Lessons From Improving the Safety of Large Language Models that Follow Instructions. arXiv:2309.07875 [cs]. Sept. 2023. DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2309.07875. URL: http://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07875 (visited on 09/15/2023)

Paul Röttger et al. XSTest: A Test Suite for Identifying Exaggerated Safety Behaviours in Large Language Models. arXiv:2308.01263 [cs]. Aug. 2023. DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2308.01263. URL: http://arxiv.org/abs/2308.01263 (visited on 09/15/2023)

Alkis Koudounas et al. "Exploring subgroup performance in End-to-End speech models". In: ICASSP 2023-2023 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP). IEEE. 2023

#### Chronologically

Please, see my Google Scholar page at https://bit.ly/gattanasio-scholar.

# Research projects

The following is a list of research projects I carried out or where I have contributed to the conceptualization of the work. Projects include collaborations with both academic peers and industry.

**Fairness in End-to-End Speech Representation Models** In this ongoing collaboration, we aim to study how modern neural end-to-end speech models (e.g., Wav2Vec 2.0 or HuBERT) behave on specific subgroups of the dataset. The end goal is to detect bias toward under-represented social groups or recording conditions where models under-perform.

Entities involved: Amazon Alexa Al.

**Gender Inclusive Communication in Italian.** E-MIMIC (Empowering Multilingual Inclusive comMuniCation) is a joint effort of classical and computational linguistics communities in fighting against non-inclusive, prejudiced language forms. We use modern transformer-based language models to learn inclusive language in written text. Currently, we focus on Academic and Public Administration Italian documents with the goal of non-inclusive content identification and rephrasing.

Entities involved: University of Turin, University of Bologna, University of Bergamo.

**Contrastive Language-Image Pre-training for the Italian Language.** During the HuggingFace JAX Community Week, we had the chance to specialize OpenAI's CLIP for the Italian language. CLIP is one of the most recent multi-modal models that connect images and text. The original model is limited to English, so we extended its capabilities. We hence presented the first CLIP model for the Italian Language, trained on more than 1.5 million high-quality image-text pairs. The released model outperforms the multilingual CLIP model on image retrieval and zero-shot classification tasks.

The project was selected among the 15 finalist projects - out of 100 - of the Flax/JAX Community Week organized by HuggingFace in partnership with Google and received a special nominee in the final evaluation round.

Entities involved: Bocconi University, University of Milano-Bicocca, University of Groningen.

**EvalRS: Rounded Evaluation of Recommender Systems** Standard evaluation metrics for Recommender Systems fail to capture important aspects, such as behavioral testing and fairness on subgroups of users. In this project, we proposed EvalRS, an open-source framework, a data challenge, and a workshop (CIKM 2022) to foster more rounded evaluations of RecSys.

Entities involved: Coveo, Coveo Labs, Stanford University, Microsoft, NVIDIA.

**Vision and Language Multi-Modality for General Fashion Concepts Learning** The cost of training tailored supervised models can be prevented by learning general representations of concepts and reusing them. We show CLIP (Contrastive Language-Italian Pre-Training) can learn general fashion concepts (e.g., long/short sleeves, high/low heels) efficiently and effectively.

Entities involved: Coveo, Coveo Labs, Stanford University, Farfetch.

**MALTO: Machine Learning at Polito.** I co-founded MAchine Learning At poliTO (MALTO), a university-funded student team at Politecnico di Torino.

The team's main goal is to participate in various data science competitions. These competitions typically involve achieving high performance on machine learning problems (e.g., classification or regression) and proposing novel, cutting-edge approaches.

Entities involved: Politecnico di Torino.

**Unsupervised Learning for Smart Fleet Management.** I joined a joint research project between my research group and the company KMaster (Telepass SpA). We designed and implemented an end-to-end machine learning and clustering-based pipeline to characterize driving behaviors and fleet management.

Entities involved: KMaster (Telepass Group).

# Public Activities & Teaching\_

#### RESEARCH COMMUNITY

#### Workshops.

- I co-organized the first edition of EvalRS: a Rounded Evaluation of Recommender Systems which has been a data challenge and workshop during CIKM 2022 (https://reclist.io/cikm2022-cup/). The event fosters a more rounded evaluation of recommender systems, encompassing aspects beyond standard evaluation, such as behavioral testing and group fairness.
- Ico-organized the third edition of the Safety for Conversational AI (https://sites.google.com/view/safety-conv-ai-workshop).

#### UNIVERSITY

**M2L School.** I co-tutored the second edition of the Mediterranean Machine Learning (M2L) Summer School, with ownership of the Natural Language Processing part. We prepared a shared notebook to guide students through 1) implementing a Transformer from scratch, 2) training the model for language modeling and machine translation, and 3) testing on gender bias.

**Teaching Assistant.** I have been a teaching assistant for several courses at Politecnico di Torino. In total, I have held 171 hours of complementary teaching.

- (2021) Data science lab: processes and methods, 60h, MD in Data Science and Engineering
- (2020) Data science lab: processes and methods, 39h, MD in Data Science and Engineering
- (2020) Business Intelligence for Big Data, 21h, MD in Industrial engineering and management
- (2019) \* Data science lab: processes and methods, 39h, MD in Data Science and Engineering
- (2019) Business Intelligence for Big Data, 21h, MD in Industrial engineering and management
- (2018) **Basi di dati**, 21h, BD in Computer Engineering
- (2018) The Fourth Industrial Revolution: Promises and Pitfalls in Blending New and Traditional Approaches in Manufacturing and Service Sectors, 30h, Alta Scuola Politecnica School

The course is the first introduction to the Python programming language and the basics of Data Science and Machine Learning libraries for MD students. We worked hard to provide students with comprehensive exercises and solutions (10 laboratories, for a total of 60+ pages of lab exercises and 250+ pages of solutions). All the material is freely available on the course website.

**Research Bites.** I have devised and contributed to the launch of Research Bites, a series of short research talks and seminars held by Ph.D. students for students of the course Data Science Lab: process and methods. The goal of RBs is to disseminate cutting-edge research topics, in short, high-level pills. The series is now in its second edition.

<sup>\*</sup> While Introduction to Databases and Business Intelligence were pre-existent and consolidated courses, I have been a major contributor in shaping *Data Science Lab: process and methods*, launched in September 2019 and currently one of the central courses in the Data Science and Engineering master degree at Politecnico.

**Master Thesis Supervisor.** I have supervised the work of 9 master students.

#### **INDUSTRY**

I have held consulting hours and courses twice.

- (2021) **Data Theory: Data Visualization with Python**Reply: Digital Services, Technology and Consulting, Turin (online)
- (2020) **Python technologies for Data Analytics**Applied Mechatronic Engineering & Technologies, Turin

#### PEER REVIEWING

I reviewed at least one work submitted to the following venues:

- ACL Rolling Review. Editions: 2021, 2022
- ACM KDD SIGKDD Conference On Knowledge Discovery And Data Mining. Editions: 2020, 2021
- ACM SIGMOD/PODS International Conference on Management of Data. Editions: 2021
- IEEE ICDE: IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering. Editions: 2020
- IEEE ICDM: IEEE International Conference on Data Mining. Editions: 2021
- ACM SAC: ACM/SIGAPP Symposium On Applied Computing. Editions: 2021
- EDBT: International Conference on Extending Database Technology. Editions: 2020, 2021
- DaWaK: International Conference on Big Data Analytics and Knowledge Discovery. Editions: 2019, 2021

I reviewed at least one work submitted to the following journals:

- Expert Systems With Applications, Elsevier
- Future Generation Computer Systems, Elsevier
- Machine Learning With Applications, Elsevier

# **Work Experience**

Kupata S.r.l. Torino, Italy

**FOUNDER** 

Nov. 2016 - 2020

• Kupata's main goal is to streamline the Lost and Found process. It brings innovation with a solution that helps people in returning items in a simple, secure, and undisclosed way. The business involves a physical object, the Kupa, and a social community that encourages members to act in the right way.

#### Consoft Sistemi S.p.A.

Torino, Italy

**CURRICULAR INTERN** 

Mar. 2016 - Jul. 2016

• I participated to the bootstrap phase of the Consoft's proprietary Knowledge Base platform. We built our solution upon Orange HRM, an open source PHP-based platform.

#### Skills

I am familiar with *italicized* entries.

**Programming** Python, C, C++, Java, C#, JavaScript, PHP, Matlab, SQL

**Deep Learning** PyTorch, Tensorflow, JAX, Keras

**Framework** Apache Hadoop, Apache Spark

Scripting Bash, Awk
DevOps AWS, GCP, Docker
Front-end Hugo, React, Dash

**Graphics** Inkscape, GIMP, *Blender, Unity 3D* **Languages** Italian, English, *Spanish, French*